■
本字幕由人人影视字幕组翻译
禁止用作任何商业盈利行为
沃德·艾伦没打中他的第一只鸭子
Ward Allen missed his first duck.
他没打中
He missed?
是的  先生
Yes, sir.
沃德·艾伦没打中他的第一只鸭子
Ward Allen missed his first duck.
得了吧  圣诞
Come on, Christmas.
这故事是约翰叔叔亲自讲给我听的
Uncle John told me the story himself.
再给我讲个故事  圣诞
Tell me another story, Christmas.
讲沃德差点杀死俄罗斯人那个
The one where Ward nearly killed that Russian.
得了  小杰克
Come on, Little Jack.
那故事我都给你讲了一百遍了
I told you that story now a hundred times.
* I said wade in the water *
* Wade in the water, children *
* Wade in the water *
* God's gonna trouble the water *
萨凡纳
* Wade in the water *
* Wade in the water, children *
翻译   阿包包
* God's gonna trouble the water *
翻译   萨凡纳野鸭
* Oh, look at those babies dressed in red *
翻译   喃喃
翻译   希希狸
* God's gonna trouble the water *
* Oh, they must have been the babies Moses led *
翻译   横排混血
* God's gonna trouble the water *
翻译   如是我闻
翻译   幸田实果子
* Wade in the water *
* Wade in water, children *
翻译   初次做电影的珞
* Wade in the water *
翻译   灰灰是菇凉
* God's gonna trouble the water *
* Oh, Jesus met the woman, met her at the well *
初校   灰灰是菇凉
* God's gonna trouble the water *
时间轴   阿好生日快乐
* He said, "Look out lady, you're headin' for hell" *
后期   IcyLisle
* God's gonna trouble the water *
阿好生日快乐
精精校精校精校
* I said wade in the water *
总监
阿好生日快乐
* Wade in the water, children *
人人影视
* Wade in the water *
YYeTs.com
* God's gonna trouble the water *
* I said God's gonna trouble the water *
* I said God's gonna trouble *
本字幕由 人人影视 字幕组翻译
* The water *
禁止用作任何商业盈利行为
改编自真实故事
拜托你得搬出去  圣诞
You got to help me out here, Christmas.
以前外边很多人认识你
Used to be people out here who knew you.
现在肯定还有人记得你
Must still be some of them around.
好吧  小杰克
All right, Little Jack.
你想听沃德·艾伦
You want to hear the story
痛打俄罗斯人的故事
about how Ward Allen beat up them Russians.
不
No.
那故事我都听了一百多遍了
I've heard that story a hundred times.
一半胡子
Half a mustache...
圣诞  他们把这片地卖了
Christmas, they sold the land.
如果你不离开那椅子
You don't get up out of that chair,
就会和房子一起
it's gonna be sitting in a pile of debris
变成废墟
with you still in it.
你会落到废墟里
That's where I'm gonna find you.
你明白吗
You understand?
小杰克  沃德·艾伦在理发椅上睡着了
Little Jack, Ward Allen fell to sleep in the barber chair,
不过在那之前  他立下了规矩
but not before he laid down the law.
他说  绝对不能
He say don't lay a finger...
动他的胡子
upon that mustache.
差点打死人了
Would have killed him, too,
亏得三名俄罗斯人扑了过来
'cept three Russians jump him.
俄国大使对沃德说
Ambassador told Ward,
"你要是再敢回俄国
"You ever come back to Russia,
我会亲自把你押到沙皇面前"
I'll march you down to the Tsar myself."
镣铐加身
In shackles.
好吧
All right.
你那些容易变质的  最好先吃
You got some perishables you better eat first.
巴布斯豌豆和羽衣甘蓝
Babs' peas and collard greens.
你不必事事操心  小杰克
You don't need be going to all that trouble, little Jack.
你到底在写什么
What'd you finally write about?
就一些圣诞曾经给我讲过的故事
Just some stories Christmas used to tell.
杰克  我跟姑娘们聊过
You know, Jack, the girls and I have been talking.
我们不认为
We don't see...
这是个好主意
That's a great idea.
你们这些姑娘们为何不自己开家小俱乐部
Why don't you girls start your own little club?
* You gotta spread joy *
* Up to the maximum *
* Bring gloom *
* Down to the minimum *
* Have faith *
* Or pandemonium's *
* Liable to walk up on the scene *
* You got to ac-cent-tchu-ate the positive *
* Eliminate the negative *
* And latch on to the affirmative *
* Don't mess with Mister In-Between *
* No, don't mess with Mister In-Between *
爸爸  能给我相机吗
Dad, can I have the camera?
我有没有给你讲过
Did I ever tell you the story
沃德·艾伦差点杀人
about how Ward Allen almost killed a man
就为了他的胡子
for cutting off his mustache?
-没有  -没吗
- No, sir. - No?
沃德·艾伦的胡子  是他骄傲与快乐的源泉
Ward Allen's mustache, that was his pride and joy.
他在一次决斗中开枪打了别人  被他父亲送去了俄国
His father had sent him to Russia for shooting a man in a duel...
不过在那之前  他立下了规矩
But not before he laid down the law.
他说  绝对不能
He say don't lay a finger
动他的胡子
upon his mustache.
差点打死人了
Would have killed him, too,
亏得三名俄罗斯人扑了过来
'cept three Russians jump him.
圣诞·穆特里比世上
Christmas Moultrie knew Ward Allen
任何一个人都更了解沃德·艾伦
better than any other person that ever lived,
虽然一个生来是庄园主
and although one to the manor born
而另一个是奴隶出身
and the other born to slavery,
他们却成了性情相投的挚友
they were kindred spirits.
从小  我就和圣诞一起打猎
As a child, I hunted with Christmas.
在河面上忙碌了一天后
After a long day on the river,
圣诞会坐在壁炉前的摇椅上
Christmas would sit in his rocker before the fireplace,
凝视着沃德的照片
gazing up at the picture of Ward,
给我们讲故事
and tell us stories.
随着我们渐渐长大  这些故事成了传奇
As we grew up, those stories became the stuff of legend.
尽管我们之中没人认识他
And though none of us were related to him,
却无一例外
there wasn't a man among us
都想要成为沃德·艾伦那样的人
who didn't wish he had a bit of Ward Allen in him.
该死的
Damn.
跟你说过要戴手套
I told you to keep your gloves on.
戴着手套我没法干活
I can't work my hands in 'em.
圣诞  这个观点毫无道理
Christmas, that sentiment has no sense about it or in it.
沃德先生  我的手太冷  拉不动它们
Mr. Ward, my hands are too cold to pull them on,
戴手套也没用
and the gloves are too cold to help.
那就撒泡尿在手上
Piss on your hands, then.
你怎么不撒在你自己手上
Why don't you piss your own?
我的手既不冷也不疼  先生
My hands are neither cold nor cut, sir,
考虑到这样  我就免做不体面的事儿了
allowing that, I can spare myself the indignity.
是啊  先生
Oh, yes, sir.
你总是免做体面的事儿
You spare yourself the dignity all the time.
"不体面"  "不"
In-dignity. In--
一样
That, too.
快上船
Get in the boat
你的说话声快把鸟儿都惊飞了
before you talk all the birds right on out of here.
这四条腿的狗可比大多数
This dog here got more manners upon four legs
在萨凡纳的两条腿的人懂礼貌
than most Savannah people walking around upon two.
我们世世代代
Generations of us have hunted
在县里的河流田野间打猎
on the river and fields of our county--
技艺代代相传
something passed between father and son.
如果历史是我们的宗教信仰
If history is our religion,
那么打猎就是其中的一件圣事
then hunting is one of its sacraments.
沃德·艾伦曾经写道
Ward Allen once wrote it down,
"这条河属于我们  我们来了"
"The river belonged to us, and we to it."
我们来了
And we to it,
就像无人付出  大教堂便无法建成
like a cathedral no hands of man could ever build.
像我这样的罪人
This is as close as a sinner like me
从未如此近距离面对上帝
will ever come to the face of God.
到了我这一代  这种传统
What became tradition for my generation
成为了一种生活方式
had once been a way of life,
对最优秀的猎人来说
and for the very best hunters,
这是谋生之道
it was a livelihood,
给萨凡纳的集市提供新鲜的飞禽
supplying the markets of Savannah with fresh fowl.
在从事这项买卖的人里
Of the men that plied that trade,
沃德和圣诞是最出色的
Ward and Christmas were the very best.
总有一天  圣诞
One of these mornings, Christmas,
你会打到你自己那份儿的
you're gonna shoot your share of these birds.
要是我就打了这些鸭子
Well, if I only shot a few of these duck,
我很乐意只管自己
I'd be happy just to carry my own,
其他的扔给你
let you handle the rest.
知道我怎么看出来的吗
See how I can tell?
那些眼里流露出惊讶的鸭子
All the ones with that surprised look in their eyes,
就是被你打到的
yeah, they're the ones you shot.
它们不敢相信这一刻终于到来了
They can't really believe it finally happened.
在鸭子的眼里我可没看出一丝惊讶  沃德先生
I don't see no surprised look in the duck eye, Mr. Ward.
看吧  你没看到  所以证明我说得对
Well, see, you don't see, so you're making my point.
我只看到一堆死鸭子
I do see that a bunch of them
看上去他们像是笑死的
look like they dead from laughing, though,
笑你足足开了七枪才打死它们
tickled to death at that silly little 7 shot you use.
圣诞  你顶着这种名字
Christmas, with a name like yours,
可不应该说出
you have a duty towards avoiding
这么讽刺的话
such sarcastic constructions.
那可不像你
They don't become you.
留着你的花言巧语去跟法官说吧
Save them $10 words for the judge.
沃德·艾伦的河和生活方式
Ward Allen's river and his way of life
本该永远这样下去
might have gone on forever
但是岁月变了  法律也变了
if time and tide and the law had not had other ideas.
而新法律与沃德不共戴天
And the new laws found in Ward an implacable opponent.
年轻人怎能为陈腐的法令所羁
Young blood doth not obey an old decree.
出自莎士比亚《空爱一场》
我们不能反抗生命的本意
We cannot cross the cause why we were born.
我们要忘记誓言  找寻自我
Let us lose our oaths to find ourselves,
否则我们会因为守誓而失去本心
or we will lose ourselves to keep our oaths.
法官大人
Your Honor.
令人难忘  艾伦先生
Well remembered, Mr. Allen,
措辞  精彩
and, nicely edited.
谢谢您  先生
Thank you, sir.
但你是生来注定要狩猎
But are you saying you were born to hunt,
还是生来注定要犯法
or saying you were born to break the law?
我的确想起某些人
I do recollect there are a few
说你在这两件事上  颇具天赋
who say you have a natural talent for both.
我读书慢  法官大人
I am slow of study, Your Honor,
如果我真的触犯了某条法律
and if there is a law I truly broke,
那我还没读到
I have not read it.
我只是狩猎技术高超
I may be a bit too good of a shot,
而有人试图以此
and there may be some who try to construe that
诽谤我的人格
against my character,
我平时多半尽力隐忍了
which efforts I generally choose to forbear.
但这种个人纠纷居然要诉之公堂
But when this type of personal dispute is deranged in such a way
简直就是莫名其妙
as to bring in front of this august assembly,
我只能说  我以名誉起誓
all I can say is, on my honor,
我的同伴和我都不想
neither my partner nor I have willingly
也不会触犯一条真正的法律
nor willfully broken a true law!
或者一条错误的法律
Or a law made in error.
错误的
Error?
谁能裁定法律是错的
And who is the judge of that?
您可以试试  先生  毫无疑问
Why you, sir, without question.
如果您乐意  会有更多"某些人"
And, if you'll allow, there are more than a few
说您在这件事上  颇具天赋
who say you have a natural talent in that regard.
天呐  救救我们吧
Lord, help us.
肃静  请肃静
Order. Order, please.
你  你指望我相信你这些说辞
You -- you expect me to believe all this?
我的名誉便是我的生命
Mine honor is my life.
二者寓于一体
Both grow in one.
夺去我的荣誉  我的生命也就不复存在
Take honor from me and my life is done.
《理查三世》
Richard III.
《理查二世》  第一幕
The Second, Act 1.
我接受指正
I stand corrected.
尽管如此  你仍然有罪
Nevertheless, you are guilty as sin.
但鉴于各方面因素
But in light of all the factors,
缓刑六个月
probation for six months...
又是这样
Not again!
在这段时期内
during which time
你必须洁身自好
you'll be pure as the driven snow.
谢谢您  法官大人
Thank you, Your Honor.
再一次  自由征服了司法
Once again, liberty plucks justice by the nose!
出自莎士比亚《一报还一报》
好了
All right.
他们本该让我们留下配额内的猎物
They could have let us keep our quota.
警长今晚能吃顿大餐了
Commissioner be eating good tonight.
这根本没道理   圣诞
There's no logic to it, Christmas.
他们指望我们把鸭子放走
They expect us to let the duck fly by
让它们飞到南美洲被别人猎杀吗
just to go and get shot in South America.
沃德先生  这只可不会
Mr. Ward, this one right here ain't gonna make it.
过来  石头
Here! Rock!
跟着
Heel.
圣诞
Christmas,
三点一刻把船停在宽阔的河段
have the skiff at Broad quarter past three and...
这只当晚饭
keep the bird for supper.
没问题
All right, then.
祝晚上愉快  沃德先生
Evening, Mr. Ward.
过来
Here!
那不算拥抱
That wasn't a hug!
我得走了
I better go now.
石头
Rock!
* I'm a Yankee Doodle, why? *
* I report back to Uncle Sam *
* So I can't shoot birds out the sky *
石头
Rock!
走吧
Come on.
乖
Good boy.
我相信你能打得跟我一样多
I'm certain you could shoot as many as me
只要你扔掉那双恶心的手套
if you give up your aversion to gloves.
我数了36只
I get 36.
订单是39只
Order was 39.
我们打了39只
We got 39.
好吧  我再数一次
Fine. I count again.
好吧  姑且算我们猎得一样多吧
All right, let's say we shot the same number
把这绝无可能的抽象现实
and leave the unlikely metaphysical ramification
留到以后再解决吧
of such a fact for another day.
那好吧
All right then.
你只管带着我
You just keep carrying me,
我搞定你的鸭子
I keep carrying your duck.
给你
There you are.
六十一块五
$61.50.
请原谅  小姐
Pardon me, mademoiselle,
我希望他没有打扰你
I, uh, hope he didn't disturb you.
不  他很讨人喜欢
No. He's delightful.
老样子  他离不开我
Just the same, he's not to leave me,
根据管理人员的安排
by arrangement of the management.
你知道的  他不该在这儿
You see, he doesn't really belong in here.
你这双靴子也不该在这儿
The same could be said for those boots.
这双靴子  少了几分个性
These boots are somewhat less headstrong.
但很跟脚
They stay better to heel.
露西  准备走了
Lucy, we're ready.
现在轮到我被叫"跟着"了
Now it's my turn to be called to "heel".
艾伦先生  你的钱
Mr. Allen, your money.
抱歉  你是沃德·艾伦先生吗
Excuse me. Are you Mr. Ward Allen?
正是在下
Yes, I am.
我们见过面吗
Have we met?
久仰你的大名
Let's just say I've met your reputation,
如雷贯耳
far and wide, in fact.
大多是传言
Lies substantially.
那你不是这条河上最好的向导
So you aren't the best guide on the river then.
不  我不是向导
No, I'm no guide at all.
我打猎为生
I am a market hunter.
是啊  你是猎人
Yes, you're the one.
我刚好有位客人
I happen to have a house guest,
一位来自弗吉尼亚州的绅士
a gentleman from Virginia.
他是斯图尔特·格雷厄姆爵士的儿子
He's the son of Sir Stuart Graham,
我们亲密的朋友和同僚
close friend and colleague,
他想在河上打猎
and he'd like to hunt our river.
随便谁都可以带他
Any fool can find it for him.
我不要随便谁
I'm not looking for just any fool.
我要最好的跟着
I'm looking for the best fool going,
他们说你是最好的  是吗
and they say that's you. Is it?
做一天的向导
A day as a guide
对我来说损失重大
is a significant loss of production from my end.
钱不是问题
Money's no object.
好吧
All right,
但是谁都不许碰我的枪
but no one touches my guns...
还有我的狗
or my dog.
好极了  那我们就这么说定了
Splendid. Then we have a deal.
我很理解你的姿态
Your gesture is deeply appreciated,
我向你保证  格雷厄姆先生装备精良
and I assure you, Mr. Graham will come well-equipped.
小心点
Careful.
那个箱子是弗吉尼亚州长送我的礼物
That bag was a gift from the Governor of Virginia.
那真该好好抱着
Then it should hold up just fine.
我不知道你们在弗吉尼亚是怎么做的
I don't know how you do this in, uh, Virginia,
但是在这  我们从来不敲锣打鼓去打猎
but here, we prefer to come unannounced.
我向你保证
I assure you,
我曾经在印度和非洲打过猎
I've hunted India, Africa.
而且我的副手一直
My steady companion...
你到底是来打猎
Are you here to hunt,
还是来向我的狗秀出身的  格雷厄姆先生
or to impress the dog with your pedigree, Mr. Graham?
要是我的消息没错  我确定没错
If my sources are correct, and I'm sure they are,
你这人有点矛盾  艾伦先生
you're a bit of a paradox, Mr. Allen.
你可是出国读过书的人
You were educated abroad,
而且还是我的母校牛津大学的高材生
at my alma mater, Oxford, in fact.
家喻户晓的"野牛比尔"
Known as Buffalo Bill,
美国陆军侦察兵  曾在八个月内猎杀近五千头野牛
竟是艾伦庄园的
yet you are the descendent
唯一继承人
and sole inheritor of the Allen plantation.
我只是一介布衣
I'm, uh, but a laborer.
靠自己的双手讨生活
I earn that I eat, get that I wear...
与世无争
owe no man hate,
清心寡欲
envy no man's happiness.
知足
Content...
常乐
with my harm.
堂堂庄园主出身
Truly of the manor born,
居然找个黑鬼做副手
and yet you choose a Negro as your steady companion.
难怪斯塔布斯先生要大老远跑去弗吉尼亚
No wonder Mr. Stubbs sent all the way to Virginia
物色良婿
to find a suitor for his daughter.
滚
Get out.
我不能
I'll do no such thing!
我向斯塔布斯小姐承诺过
I promised Miss Stubbs
要给她打只新鲜的野味
a fresh bird for her table.
你得保证我履行我的诺言
It is your job to ensure that I keep that promise.
我得提醒你  你只是个拿钱办事的向导
May I remind you that you are a paid guide?
好猎人举了枪
No good hunter takes a shot
必定弹无虚发
unless he knows he can't miss.
滚
Get out.
你不会有好下场
You have not heard the last of this.
恐怕斯塔布斯先生要找你麻烦喽
You likely stirred up trouble now with Mr. Stubbs.
你是不是有个表亲在斯塔布斯家做厨子
Don't you have a cousin that cooks for Stubbs?
的确是有
Not saying I don't,
但她从来不跟我谈起她与她无关的事
but she'd never talk about nothin' wasn't her business.
是啊  你也一样
That's right. You, either.
是啊
That's right.
所以你对斯塔布斯家的小姐一无所知
That's why you wouldn't know nothin' about Stubbs' daughter.
把莱纳家小伙儿迷得颠三倒四那妞么
The one that turned down Lynah's boy?
你表亲绝对没跟你说过这事儿
Which your cousin never told you about.
没错
Exactly.
瞧瞧啊
Look at that.
哎呦喂  居然自己寻着路回来了
Doodly doo, found his way home.
先生  悠着点儿
Now, sir, account for yourself.
晚上好  治安官先生  斯塔布斯先生
Evening, Mr. Sheriff, Mr. Stubbs.
我们说好了  艾伦
We had a deal, Allen.
的确是说好了
Yes, we did.
说要带一位绅士到河上
To take a gentleman on the river.
然而  格雷厄姆先生根本不是什么绅士
However, Mr. Graham proved to be no gentleman at all.
我恐怕他羞辱了您
See, I feared he'd bring embarrassment to you
和您可爱的家人
and your lovely family.
他大放阙词说他一心觊觎令爱
boasting as it were over his intentions towards your daughter.
我毅然决然拒绝带路
I--I--I resolutely refused
绝不能用您的钱助纣为虐  先生
to take a cent of your money, sir.
能借一步吗
Please, if you will...
要是我的判断没错的话
If I had exercised my better judgment,
你完全可以避免
you would not have been exposed
陷入如此尴尬的境地
to this public embarrassment.
愿闻其详
Appreciate that.
您如果想要野鸭  只管开口
I'd be pleased if you'd take a pair of mallards for your table.
我们的厨子正愁没鸭子下锅呢
Our cook does do wonders with waterfowl.
我一早给您送去
First thing in the morning, then.
嘎  嘎  嘎
Quack quack quack.
艾伦先生
Mr. Allen.
什么风把你吹来了啊
What happy accident brings you here?
我答应给令尊送新鲜的野鸭来
I promised your father some fresh duck.
看得出你很守信
A promise well kept, I see.
你还带了你的小伙伴来
Look, you brought your friend.
它好像挺高兴见到我
He seems glad to see me.
样子虽呆  脑子聪明
He's smarter than he looks.
确实
Indeed.
保不齐它还会引用莎士比亚呢
Next thing I know, he'll be quoting Shakespeare.
请转告令尊
Please tell your father
把子弹从鸭子身体里取出来
to remove the shot from the birds
或者告诉厨师  随便你了
or tell your cook, whatever you plans.
日安  斯塔布斯小姐
Good day, Miss Stubbs.
艾伦先生  我想邀请
Mr. Allen, I wish to inquire, uh--
父亲
Father.
守信之人
A man of his word.
的确
Indeed.
我此前还犹豫是否应该让艾伦先生
I was on the verge of asking Mr. Allen
做我们的向导
for a guide on the river.
艾伦先生  我还从来没在河上
You see, Mr. Allen, I've never seen the city
仔细欣赏过这个城市
from the perspective of the river,
听说景色非常美
and I'm told it's quite beautiful.
我父亲可不是划船高手
And Father here has no inclination towards rowing.
露西  艾伦先生忙于事业  时间金贵
Lucy, I'm sure Mr. Allen's time would be better spent at his enterprise.
谢谢  沃德  谢谢你的鸭子
Thanks very much, Ward, for the duck.
我敢肯定这会是相当美味的一餐
I'm sure it will be a meal to remember.
我觉得为表感谢
The least we can do then
我们至少应该邀请艾伦先生共进晚餐
is invite Mr. Allen for supper.
周日吧  德索托
Sunday? The DeSoto?
中午见
Noon, then.
好吧
All right.
柏拉图曾经把人的心灵
Plato likens the mind of man
比喻成鸟儿的天堂
to an aviary of birds,
而鸟儿则是浩瀚无垠的知识
and birds to kinds of knowledge.
我发觉知识真是令人琢磨不透
I find it a queer thing, knowledge,
因为不论逻辑是多么的严密
because no matter how tight the logic,
总是会有特例出现
there's always the errant fact,
就像
like--like--
就像一只孤雁
like a solitary bird,
离开雁群  独自踏上冒险之旅
separated from the flock in search of adventure.
你的意思是鸟也有理性
Are you suggesting birds can reason?
紧随渴望的理性是什么呢
What is reason next to yearning?
那个  跟我说说  艾伦
Yes. Well, ahem... tell me, Allen,
你明明是出国留学的高材生
with all this foreign education under your belt,
怎么会自甘选择
how is it you choose to subject yourself
严酷的野外生活
to the rigors of an outdoor life?
为什么要选择压抑闭塞的办公室生活呢
Why not embrace the joys of the airless boardroom?
至少不用担心刮风下雨啊
Well, the rewards are not subject to the whims of nature.
和人心的风雨比起来
But instead on the whims of man's nature.
我觉得自然界的风雨更易掌握
I find nature's nature far more predictable
更加  坦城
and far more, uh, honest.
也是
Fair enough.
有几分道理
Can't argue with that.
不过  你毕竟还是有着
Still, you do seem to have a talent
演讲和辩论的天赋
for discourse and persuasion.
我有幸曾在法庭上
I could see you being very successful
一睹你的风采
in the courtroom, for instance.
我年轻时  曾浪费大好时光
As a boy, I wasted many beautiful days
在枯燥的律师办公室工作
in a dusty law office,
全是我父母的安排
by arrangement of my parents.
他们一心想要我干这一行
They were bent on my entering the profession.
追随约翰·艾略特·沃德光辉的脚步是吗
Following the footsteps of the Honorable John Eliot Ward, no less?
你似乎从他那里继承了一个
You seem to have inherited from him
名叫圣诞·穆特里的好黑奴
a fine servant in Christmas Moultrie.
我叔叔认为圣诞是极好的向导
My uncle saw in Christmas an accomplished guide,
所以聘请了他
and he hired him for his services.
如果非要说是继承
If anyone did the inheriting,
应该是圣诞继承了我
it was Christmas of me.
你就非要打破常规  是吧  艾伦
You turn everything on its head, don't you, Allen?
真是叛逆
Quite the rebel.
但是我觉得你说得太夸张了点
And here I thought you'd been exaggerated.
出自莎士比亚《奥赛罗》
"男人应当言如其实"
"Well, men should be what they seem."
"如若不然  此人定一无所是"
"Or those that be not, would not they be none?"
我觉得这样很好
I think it's absolutely delightful--
学者回归自然
a man of letters who's returned to nature.
颇有几分"公民的不服从"之风骨
And a sprinkle of civil disobedience for good measure.
如果你是在暗示
If you are suggesting
我就像现代版的梭罗  那你错了
I'm some sort of contemporary Thoreau, you are mistaken.
梭罗著有《论公民的不服从》  后隐居瓦尔登湖
我并无目的
I have no agenda.
我只是单纯喜欢这种生活
I simply prefer this life.
圣诞
Christmas!
治安官从欧利希的店里抢走了我们的猎物
The sheriff stole our order from Ehrlich's store.
沃德先生
Mr. Ward?
我老实工作  这算什么罪
I am guilty of nothing but an honest day's work,
而他居然从餐桌上抢走了别人的晚餐
while he steals a meal right off a man's table.
沃德先生
Mr. Ward!
我真想写一篇社论投给报社
I have a good mind to write the editor of the paper,
别以为我不会写
and don't think I won't.
原谅我打扰了
I beg your pardon.
我觉得给报社投稿是个好主意
I think writing to the paper's a fine idea.
斯塔布斯小姐想请我们为她服务
Miss Stubbs here hired our services.
做什么
To do what?
别担心  艾伦先生
Don't worry, Mr. Allen.
我只是想为我的花园采集一些野花
I simply wish to collect cuttings for my garden.
野花在城市的花园里能养好吗
A wildflower can be cultivated in a city garden?
只要栽培方法得当
With the right nurturing,
没有什么不能被教养好
most anything can be cultivated.
我先把这些猎物送到德索托
I better get these birds here over to the DeSoto
免得治安官把它们也拿走了
before the Sheriff lock them up, too.
下午愉快  斯塔布斯小姐
Good afternoon, Miss Stubbs.
好的圣诞
Christmas.
我见过艺术家们的描绘
I've seen artists' renderings,
但没想到它会这么美
but I had no idea.
如同泛舟于星河之上
It's like floating on a sea of stars.
这香气
And that perfume.
好像星星是由糖果做成的
It's like stars made of sugar.
星岛
Starry archipelagoes...
极美星空
raving skies.
没错
Yes.
极美星空
Raving skies.
父亲在我的花园里建了一座日光浴室
My father built a solarium for my garden.
我小时候  不能随意出门
When I was a little girl, I couldn't be outside,
那日光浴室大得像永远填不满
and the solarium seemed impossibly large to fill,
我画得满溢出来了
but I filled it till bursting.
等满到没有地方可以画画后
And when there was no more room for planting,
我就躺在地板中央
I laid down in the middle of the floor,
藏在花丛之下
buried beneath the flowers
想象我自己正在飞翔
and imagined I was flying.
飞毯
A flying carpet.
你知道瓦斯涅佐夫的画作
You know Vasnetsov's painting?
是的
Yeah.
我父亲认识俄国大使
My father knew the Russian Ambassador.
他曾绘声绘色地描述过那幅画的每个细节
He described it in such vivid detail,
让我感觉就像是亲眼所见一般
I felt like I'd seen it with my own two eyes.
你肯定认识俄国大使吧
Now, you must have known the Russian Ambassador.
父亲说你在俄国生活过
Father says you were in Russia?
我第一次藏在花丛下的时候
The first time I disappeared beneath the flowers,
父母找不到我
my parents couldn't find me.
父亲差点心脏病发
Father nearly had a heart attack,
他要保护我的整个人生
He'd spent my whole life trying to
不受各种他所想象出的恐怖伤害
protect me from all kinds of imagined horrors,
但我却凭空消失了
and there I had vanished into thin air.
那是我的避难所
It was my refuge.
如果我是野鸟的话  你抓不住我
If I were a bird, you wouldn't catch me.
我认得出诱饵
You see, I recognize a decoy when I see one.
那  我会是什么样的鸟呢
So, what kind of bird would I be?
你说什么
I beg your pardon?
如果我是一只野鸟  而你在狩猎我
If I were a bird and you were hunting me,
我会是什么样的鸟
what would I be?
野鸭
A mallard.
飞翔时美得无与伦比
Particularly beautiful bird in flight.
就这样吗  不过是一堆华美的羽毛
That's all? Just a bunch of pretty feathers?
不
No.
我欣赏那些鸟依靠自己的
I enjoy a bird that uses its,
慧黠躲过狩猎者
native cunning to outwit the hunter.
野鸭很慧黠
A mallard has canny.
这样啊
I see.
我觉得这其中是有深意的
There's some meaning in it, I think.
我不知道我能否准确描述出来  但是
I don't know if I can put my finger on it, but...
有时我觉得自己就在那里
sometimes I feel as if I'm up there,
追逐着某种
pulling toward some...
遥远的目标
distant purpose.
教我射击吧
Teach me to shoot.
什么
What?
不是打鸟  打个目标
Not a bird, a... a target.
那边的那只旧货船  装了东西吗
That old barge over there, is it loaded?
当然了  小心点
Of course, it is. Careful, now...
来  抓住这个  来
Here! Grab this, here!
抓住
Grab it.
抓住枪杆
Grab the gun.
抓紧了
Hold on.
好了  好了
Good. Good.
你不会游泳
You can't swim.
别担心  这是我们的秘密
Don't worry, it'll be our secret.
这不是秘密
It's not a secret.
只是没被公开的事实
It's just not a publicized fact.
"事实坦荡存于我的心胸之中"
"Truth hath a quiet breast."
出自莎士比亚《理查二世》
你很不寻常  沃德·艾伦
You're a rare man, Ward Allen.
我觉得你引用名句的功力不错
And while I do find your word play entertaining to a point,
但我可不是个耐心的女人
I'm not a patient woman.
你能记住吗
Can you remember that?
我会的
I will.
你能记住以后别碰我的枪吗
Can you remember not to touch my guns?
好吧
Yes, I can.
那就好
Okay, then.
好
Yes.
我决心已定了  父亲
I've made my decision, Father.
你回绝了许多大有前途的追求者  露西
You've ruined so many prospects, Lucy.
不过是些稚气未脱的男孩
Nothing but boys,
对他们的父辈亦步亦趋
following in their father's footsteps.
我在生活开始之前就知道未来了
I'd know my life before I had even lived it.
那男人是个粗人
The man's a boor.
沃德·艾伦拒绝了一笔丰厚的遗产
Ward Allen walked away from a fine inheritance.
上帝知道为什么
God knows why.
他想要自由
He wanted to be free.
自由
Free?
他的黑奴自由了
His Negro's free.
父亲
Father!
露西  别再说了
Lucy, don't say anymore.
我们今年去避暑的时候再谈这事
Let's talk this over while we're away this summer.
我不会陪你去葡萄园  母亲
I won't be accompanying you to the Vineyard, Mother.
我不会任由你们摆布
I am neither yours to dispense nor to withhold.
沃德·艾伦夫人
Mrs. Ward Allen!
你的美丽惊动了夜晚
Your beauty startles the night!
我会迅速绕地球一圈再回来
I shall make a quick loop around the Earth and return!
-准备好  -你敢
- Prepare! - Don't you dare!
-别吃洋葱和大蒜  -阻止那个人
- Eat no onions nor garlic... - Stop that man!
因为我们要保持气息甜美
for we are to utter sweet breath.
我会的  只要他停止开枪
I will, soon as he stops shootin'.
让路
Make way!
他们应该在那里等我们
They should be there waiting for us.
多谢让我留宿  警官
Much obliged for the sleep, Officer.
我的荣幸  沃德
My pleasure, Ward.
希望那位女士已经准备好接纳你了
Hope the little lady's ready to receive you.
跟女人吵架是赢不了的  你知道吧
You know, a woman ain't an argument to win, don't you?
那些花招哄不好露西小姐的
One of these decoys here ain't gonna bring Miss Lucy in.
但她架不住甜言蜜语  圣诞  女人嘛
But for thy sweet understanding, Christmas, a woman.
你简直是野兽
You're a perfect beast!
露西
Lucy.
Lucy?
露西  让我进去
Lucy, let me in!
你可以跟狗一起睡
You can sleep with the dog!
那就是你该去的地方
That's where you belong!
你应该跟石头订婚
It's Rock you should have betrothed!
拜托  亲爱的  至少让我进去
Please, my dear, at least let me in
给我一点隐私
behind the privacy of closed doors.
隐私
Privacy?
你觉得萨凡纳还有人
Do you think there's a soul in Savannah
不知道你大半夜把我扔在一边
that doesn't know you left my side in the middle of the night
跑去狂饮威士忌吗
to wallow in a vat of whiskey?
好吧  露西
Now, Lucy...
你说得对
You're right.
我自我发泄以控制情绪
I--I temper myself to keep my temper,
是因为我需要让自己冷静下来
and if I need to water myself down at times,
承认吧
Admit it.
小男人勾不起你的兴趣
A smaller man could never hold your interest.
我就这样  爱慕着你
As I am, I adore you.
你表现得可真像
How well you show it.
你想让我怎么做
What would you have me do?
出自莎士比亚《约翰王》
为纯金镀上金箔
To gild refined gold,
替纯洁的百合花涂上粉彩
to paint the lily...
给紫罗兰的花瓣洒上香水
to throw perfume on the violet...
替彩虹添加一道颜色
to add another hue into the rainbow.
实在是多此一举
Wasteful and ridiculous...
浪费而可笑
excess.
* It's cold *
* Now I lost my lover *
* And where shall I find her? *
抱歉我来晚了  穆特里先生
Pardon the tardiness, Mr. Moultrie.
来晚好过不来  沃德先生
Late's still better than never, Mr. Ward.
* Bring me a gator *
* Girl, when you get off the island *
* A ringtail 'ator *
* Oh, when you get off the island *
好了
Clear.
* A Darien gator *
* Girl, when you get off the island *
* Ohh, when you get off the island *
行了  就这些了
All right, that's it.
这是全部了
That's the last of them.
欧利希店要的十只  德索托要的二十只
That's 10 for Ehrlich's, 20 for the DeSoto.
这个捕猎季就要结束了
That's almost a quarter.
那见鬼的是什么
What the hell was that?
是莱纳老头
It's Old Man Lynah!
我不是说了不要进他的领地吗
Ain't I tell you not to get on his property?
他知道是我们  沃德先生
He knows it's us, Mr. Ward!
如果他知道是我们  为什么还开枪
If he knows it's us, why is he shootin'?
他气你跟露西小姐在一起
He's mad about you hitchin' up with Miss Lucy,
这就是原因
that's why.
我可帮了他大忙
I did that man a favor.
露西能把他儿子生吞了
Lucy'd eat his boy for lunch.
反正他就是生气
All the same, he all worked up,
你是最好的出气筒
and you the best one to blame!
太荒唐了
This is ridiculous.
我们得离开
Let's get out of here.
莱纳先生  停战
Mr. Lynah, uh...truce!
停战
Truce.
我们马上  我们马上就走
We'll just- We'll be on our way.
石头  过来
Rock! Here!
对  我们  我们马上就走
Yeah. We'll--We'll be on out of here.
过来  上来
Here! Go on up!
过来  过来
Here. Here.
过来  坐下  到这来
Come! Sit. Come here.
过来
Here!
圣诞  从莱纳开枪后你还没说过话
Christmas, you haven't said a word since Lynah's.
是  先生
No, sir.
为什么
Why?
我没什么可说的  先生
I got nothin' to say, sir.
你会没话说
Since when?
我只能说
All I'm saying is,
如果当时只有我  情况会不一样
it would have been different it was just me.
你还在为那件事生气
You still mad about that?
我只是说说而已
All I'm for saying is.
听好了
Listen up now.
莱纳是想冲我开枪
Lynah was aiming to hit me,
而且这里的每个人
and every man around here
都有权捍卫自己的领地
has a right to defend his own property.
那好吧
All right, then.
下午好  沃德先生
Afternoon, Mr. Ward.
那种主张是完全荒谬的
It is an absolute preposterous statement
居然以为如果我不在场情况会不一样
the outcome would have been different had I not been there.
莱纳瞄准的是我  好吗
Lynah was aimed to shoot me, all right?
他没打中  我们脱身了
He missed and we got away!
不  先生  是你脱身了
No, sir, you got away!
我只是跟着你  就像这条狗一样
I just be along there with you like the dog here!
就算我不在场
If I hadn't been there,
他不会把石头追下河杀掉
he wouldn't have chased Rock down the river and killed him!
当然不会  先生  他会让你的狗活着
No, sir, he would have let your dog live!
我只是说
All I'm sa...
你的世界跟我不一样  明白吗
Your world ain't mine, you understand?
需要我帮忙吗  艾伦先生
Can I be of any assistance, Mr. Allen?
给我一杯威士忌
Gimme a whiskey.
你为什么打猎  先生
Why do you hunt, sir?
那是绅士的运动
It's a gentleman's sport.
让你觉得是在运动  对吧
Makes you feel sporty, does it, huh,
射杀一两只野鸟
to shoot a bird or two?
你了解野鸟吗
Do you know these birds?
你能分辨出灰背鸭和褐颈鸭吗
Can you tell a canvasback from a widgeon
通过它们空中转折的姿态
from the way it turns in the air,
通过它们猎食的方式
from how it feeds?
你知道它们经历的旅程
Do you know the journeys they take,
它们的决心
their determination,
包裹在那小小胸脯里的坚定意志
power of will wrapped up in that small little breast
你开枪时根本毫不在意
you fill so carelessly with shot?
是吧
Do you?
听听  一个高尚的野蛮人
Listen to you, the original noble savage.
你什么都不知道
You know nothin',
你什么都不去想
and you think about nothin'.
我猎杀二百只鸭子光明坦荡
200 taken my way is an honest act.
是我们两个种族诞生起延续至今的交易
It is a transaction as old as our two species.
我知道我在做什么
See, I know what I do.
而你哪怕只猎杀两只鸟
Two single birds taken your way,
那也叫屠杀
now, that's what I call a slaughter.
枪械库应该有枪
A gun room has guns in it!
家也应该有丈夫
And a home has a husband in it.
约翰·艾略特·沃德  冠以胜利而背负牺牲的一生
约翰先生说你很令人担忧
Mr. John says you was worrisome.
我叔叔还说什么了  穆特里先生
What else did my uncle say, Mr. Moultrie?
叫我圣诞就行
Call me Christmas that's all.
圣诞
Christmas.
约翰先生说他们不收夏鸭
Mr. John say they won't take the summer duck.
要我不猎鸭除非太阳从西边出来
Hell will freeze over before they take mine.
就算把我告到最高法院我也不会妥协
I'll take it all the way to the Supreme Court if I have to.
"年轻人怎能为陈腐的法令所羁"
Young blood doth not obey an old decree.
"我们不能反抗生命的本意"
We cannot cross the cause why we were born.
法官先生  短吻鳄猎鸭没有限制
Mr. Judge, the alligator got no limit,
浣熊猎鸭也没有限制
and the raccoon ain't got no limit,
为什么圣诞就要有限制呢
so why should Christmas have a limit?
这是件严肃的事  圣诞
This is serious, Christmas.
我不能总是判你们缓刑
Repeated probationary sentences cannot be supported.
大人  看守人罗西尼奥尔明确宣称
Sir, Warden Rossignol clearly states
他于日落时分在近200米的距离外认出了我
that he identified me at the distance of 200 yards at sunset.
法官大人  这是无可争辩的事实
Your Honor, this is a matter of undisputed fact.
容我说一句  法官大人
Excuse me, Your Honor,
这些才是无可争辩的事实
but the undisputed facts are these.
近200米  日落时分
200 yards, sunset,
野草这时节都长到这么高
saw grass this time of year this high.
猎鸭的人
Person firing at ducks,
站在这么深的沼泽地里
who must have stood at least this deep in the mire,
也就是说  在近200米的距离
meaning that at 200 yards,
看守人罗西尼奥尔也许能辨认出
Warden Rossignol might deduce
开枪的是上帝创造出的人类
what species of God's creation fired the gun,
但绝对分不出是男是女
but would not have been able to sex the shooter,
更别说认出他  或她
much less identify him...or her.
或是县里任何一个拥有猎枪的人
Or anyone for that matter who owns a shotgun in the county.
对了  法官大人
By the way, Your Honor,
您还留着那把格林纳尔步枪吗
you still own that Greener?
是的
Yes, I do.
制作精良啊  是吧
Yeah, it's beautifully made, isn't it?
没错
Yes.
如果英国国王做得跟他们的枪一样好
If the English made kings the way they made guns,
咱现在还是殖民地呢
we'd still be a colony.
法官大人
Your Honor!
是的  是的  是的
Of course, of course. Of course.
圣诞
Christmas,
你知道猎杀夏鸭违反法律吗
you knew it was against the law to shoot summer duck.
我知道  法官大人
Yes, sir.
圣诞  那你当时为什么
Christmas, why then did you not
不舍弃鸭子
dispose of the ducks?
先生
Sir?
我是说  圣诞
What I mean is, Christmas,
你见到看守人来了
when you saw the warden coming,
为什么不丢掉夏鸭
why didn't you throw away the summer duck?
法官先生  您肯定没吃过夏鸭吧
Mr. Judge, you must never ate a summer duck.
本案驳回
Case dismissed.
来啊  打开
Go on, open it.
你的枪与雄辩已无用武之地  沃德
You've nothing left to prove with guns and bluster, Ward.
换种武器吧
Try a different weapon.
他们在建新工厂
They're building a new factory.
帝国
Imperial.
帝国个屁
Imperial, my ass.
他们只留下那一块地
They cleared all but that patch over there.
老板的新猎场
The boss man's new hunting ground.
那些傻瓜也不想想
What kind of fool thinks a duck,
从这儿到大沼泽地有那么多低地
with all the low country from here to the Everglades,
鸭子干嘛偏要往那块混凝土飞
is gonna fly in that concrete patch?
这儿没法打猎了
It's no good here.
石头呢
Where's Rock?
石头
Rock!
我最后一次见到他
Last I seen him,
是在那棵树边上
he was over by that tree there.
沃德先生
Mr. Ward...
石头总是尽职尽责
Rock always done us his best.
如今它完成了最后的使命
Now he done his last.
莎士比亚都不可能说得比你好  圣诞
Shakespeare could not have said it better, Christmas.
"猎鸭人如何避免成为罪犯"
"How a Duck Hunter Avoids Being a Sinner."
我有没有告诉你我找到
Did I tell you I found
沃德在报纸上发表的一些文章
some of Ward's newspaper articles?
听听这个
Listen to this.
题目叫"猎鸭人如何避免成为罪犯"
Called "How the Duck Hunter Avoids Being a Sinner."
"随着各种有关猎鸭的
"With all sorts of unreasonable
不合理的荒谬法令出台
and absurd restrictions on duck shootin' now,
人们要在短暂的渔猎期猎鸭
fella can't go out in the short open season
就会违反那些愚蠢的禁止条令
without transgressing some of the fool don'ts.
想要避免成为罪犯  最安全的方法
So the safest way to avoid being a sinner
是当他去猎鸭时
when a fella goes duck shootin',
不开一枪"
is not to shoot anything at all".
沃德很高产
Yeah, Ward was prolific.
用露西送他的钢笔阻挡时代的洪流
Holding back the tide with that fountain pen Lucy gave him.
是啊  努力阻挡
Yeah. Trying to, anyway.
大家都腾空了阁楼
Everybody's emptying out their attics
用来给莱拉开历史学会
for Lila's historical society.
霍默用二百个板条箱给她建了一个
Homer built her, got to be 200 crates.
没收一分钱
Won't take a nickel for them.
霍默他爸也是一样
Homer's daddy the same.
用几把旧枪抵消了沃德的账务
Settled Ward's account for a couple of old guns.
我爸参加搜救队找到了沃德的遗体
You know, my daddy was on the search party found Ward's body.
说发现他时  他正穿着睡衣
Said he found him in-- wearing his pajamas.
有人说那不是事故
Some say it wasn't an accident.
那是什么
What is?
是啊
Yeah.
不管沃德在寻找什么
Whatever it is Ward was searching for...
都已离他远去
it eluded him.
不如把那幅也拿去吧
Might as well add that to your collection.
圣诞  我
Christmas, I...
我给你找了个住处
I found you a place to live.
很舒适
It's comfortable.
虽然不是家  但我尽力安排了
It's not home, but I made sure of it.
你住在那儿会很舒服
You're gonna be comfortable.
好吧
All right.
我跟你说什么来着  圣诞
What'd I tell you about the fire, Christmas?
我走以后别犯懒
Don't get lazy while I'm gone
别让火熄灭
and let it burn out.
* Jack t' the rack back, stickit ball a hack *
* Low ball high ball, scallion Jack *
* Low ball high ball, scallion... *
我就像个猎人
But I feel like a hunter
一枪惊飞了两群鸟
with two coveys flushed at once!
所以  我问你们  我该朝哪边射击
So, I ask you, which way do I shoot?
反正别射你同行的猎人  看在上帝的份上
Not at your fellow hunter, for God's sake.
你说什么
What'd you say?
应该瞄准制定这条可恶法律的城里人吗
Then at the city bird that created this abominable law?
他只会虚张声势
Why, his is but empty bravado,
故作姿态
amateur posturing.
那玩意儿有着鸭的脚
A creature with duck's feet,
蛇的心  驴的蠢
snake's heart and an ass's disposition.
不
No!
是我们这些乡下人
It is our country cousin who,
未能尽责使用自己的枪
by failing to be conscientious in the use of his gun,
才使得城里人制定了这条可怕的法律
has made our city cousin write this dreaded law.
哎呦喂
Doodly doo.
你好  露西小姐
Hello, Miss Lucy.
无论你认为你在逃避什么
Whatever it is you think you're hidin' from...
我才没有逃避
I'm doin' no such thing.
你知道在哪儿能找到我
You know exactly where to find me.
我不是说你在逃避我
I don't mean from me.
那是什么
What, then?
我了解你  沃德·艾伦
I see you, Ward Allen.
我知道你的能力
I see what you're capable of,
我看得出你现在离目标有多远
and I see how far you've missed the mark.
亲爱的  你在质疑我的枪法吗
Sweetheart, you questioning my marksmanship?
我在质疑你的选择
I question your choices,
尤其是那些会让你英年早逝的选择
especially the ones that will send you to an early grave.
女人  你当我是你的哈巴狗
Woman, you'd have me your lap dog,
坐在你的脚边  唯命是从
sittin' at your heels, fetchin' at your command.
我告诉你  大小姐
I tell you what, little lady,
就连猎犬也有自己的本能
even a retriever must have its own instincts,
按自己的意愿行动
act on its own accord,
只要它是只称职的猎犬
if it's to be worth its salt.
把你自己比成狗还真是恰当
Apropos you would liken yourself to a dog.
汪  我是自己的主宰
Woof! I am my own master.
别管我  女人
Leave me be, woman.
绝不
Never.
我说话你就得听
You will if I say so.
你要开枪打我吗
So you'll shoot me?
还了解我吗
See me now?
按原告所述
By the plaintiff's own admission,
事发当日
on the day in question,
据其亲眼所见
and by her own eyewitness account,
她声称是我
she has established it was I
准确无误地射穿了这幅画像的眼睛
that shot out cleanly the eyes of this portrait
在距离
from a distance of no less than...
十五步之远
15 paces,
我们的客厅是屋子里最大的房间
our parlor being the largest room in the house.
测试一个人是否清醒有很多方法
There are many tests of a man's relative sobriety.
而我告诉各位  这样的枪法
And I offer to you that such a piece of marksmanship
就是测试方法之一
belongs among those tests.
由此只能推断出
It can only be deduced then
这位尊敬的夫人所做的陈述
that the esteemed lady is incorrect
自相矛盾
in one statement or the other.
要么是我醉了
Either I was drunk!
要么是我开的枪
Or I made these shots.
但是毋庸置疑
But most certainly...
毋庸置疑  这两种陈述
most certainly, the two statements stand
互相矛盾
as mutually incompatible assertions.
太荒谬了
This is ridiculous!
艾伦先生  你作为一名神枪手声名在外
Mr. Allen, your reputation as a marksman is well established.
显然  我无须枉法或误判
And clearly, I would not have to bend the law or my judgment
可以直接驳回指控  放你走人
very far to dismiss the charge and send you on your way.
华丽的逻辑并不能改变事实
Fancy logic does not change the truth!
请坐  艾伦夫人
Sit down, please, Mrs. Allen.
放开我
Get off of me!
但是  我发现为了公众安全的利益
However, I find it in the interest of public safety
必须判你有罪
to call you guilty...
什么
What?!
判你入狱十天
and put you in jail for 10 days.
听啊  听啊
Hear, hear!
肃静  肃静
Order. Order.
-这是暴行  -上前来
- This is an atrocity. - Approach.
现在就上前
Approach now.
十天估计还不够平息她的怒火
10 days may not be enough to cool her off.
我要是你  我会把这十天用来
If I were you, I would spend those 10 days
利用文字构建一个王国
using my way with words to conjure up one big Kingdom
祈祷自己得到救赎
come prayer for your salvation.
我  沃德·艾伦  错了
I, Ward Allen, was wrong.
我  沃德·艾伦  也许错了
I, Ward Allen, may have been wrong.
在你去查看
Before you check to see
太阳有没有从西边出来之前
if the fires of hell have turned to ice,
我想强调  我将会
let me emphasize that I would do
或是说我已经
or have done
不会对我的生活做任何改变
nothing different in my life.
但似乎我们的世界
But it seems that perhaps our world
到了分岔路口
met a fork in the road,
世界选择了一条路
and the world took one path,
而我选了另一条
and I took the other.
也许这个结果无法避免
Perhaps this is an inevitable result,
我们每个人都注定会发觉
and each of us are doomed to find ourselves
到头来  都是一个人独行
on a path alone in the end,
尤其是那些认为世界
especially those of us who found the world as it was
近乎完美的人
to be a close to perfect place--
那些接受世事起伏的人
those who accepted that the affairs of men
就像一条河流
are like those of a river,
在那里  岁月是生命的终极塑造者
where time and tide are the ultimate shapers of a life,
在那里  繁衍  迁徙  甚至是死亡
where procreation, migration, and even death
皆由着上帝的意愿
are spokes of the same wheel
随着历史的车轮滚滚前行
that turns in heaven's vault just the way it should.
但有一些人却决意要
But there are others who are determined
重造车轮  逆流而上
to reshape that wheel and turn back the tide,
他们似乎已经准备好了
and they appear ready to do it.
也许他们是对的  他们也这么做了
Maybe they are right, representing as they do,
胸口涌起的冲动
an impulse in the breast of man
驱动着人类无止境工业化的脚步
that drives our species toward restless industry.
也许我们的存在是为了再造一切
Maybe we are here to remake everything,
重塑一切
reshape everything,
创造我们自己对于完美的新理念
create our own new idea of perfection
把上帝的旨意留在历史的阴影之中
and leave God's idea to the dim shades of history.
也许我  一直在与新理念作斗争
And maybe I, having fought against that new idea,
拒绝那理念
rejected that idea,
觉得那理念可憎
found that idea abhorrent,
也许我错了
maybe I was wrong.
但我并不这么认为
But I do not think so.
因为我相信  如果人类整体取得了进步
Because I believe if we have grown as a species,
那是因为承受了野性的洗礼
it has been because of the test of wildness,
如果我们将野性重塑成温和
and if we succeed in remaking wildness into mildness,
那我们将走向衰落
then we will begin to diminish.
但我所做的一切换来的
But all I have accomplished
不过是双伤痕累累的拳头
is a broken knuckle or two
伤害了我和我的爱人
and hurting myself and my own
而非我的本意目标
more than those who are the target of my calumny.
所以  也许我应该
So, perhaps I do better
钻研那些书卷
to take my pokes on these pages
并且听从莎翁的指引
and take direction from the Bard--
"让你的墨水里掺满怨毒"
"Let there be gall enough in thy ink."
出自莎士比亚《第十二夜》
值得一试
It's worth a try.
萨凡纳市立监狱
你  读了我的文章吗
Did you read my article?
是的
Yes.
好
Good.
就这样
Is that all?
我不会再受屈了
I won't be disgraced again.
作为一个母亲那样不合适
It's not befitting a mother.
布莱森医生已经确定了
Doctor Bryson is sure.
什么
What?
别急着说话  沃德
Don't speak right now, Ward.
我要你仔仔细细地想想你现在的感受
I want you to think very, very carefully about how you feel,
因为我可不能忍受
because I can't bear for you to tell me
你对我说谎
anything less than God's own truth.
* Oh, bring me a gator *
* Girl, when you come off the island *
* Whoa, just a ringtail 'ator *
* Just a Darien gator *
* Girl, when you come off the island *
* Oh, girl, when you come off the island *
配额就这些了
That's the quota.
欧利希店要的十二只
12 for Ehrlich's store,
德索托要的二十只
20 for the De Soto.
之后  他们会把这些野鸭子
Next thing you know, they'll make us buy
通过杂货店再卖给我们
the duck we shot back from the grocery store,
而且价格是我们卖给他们的两倍
twice what they paid us in the first place.
圣诞
Christmas...
看看那个
Would you look at that!
露西那天看到的船
Lucy's barge.
露西打中了
Lucy hit it.
真不敢相信
I'll be damned.
绝对是这艘船最传奇的故事了
One of the more improbable stories this old boat's got to tell.
你觉得这船还能航行吗
You reckon she's seaworthy?
要说漂浮  那应该可以
It'll float, that's what you mean.
圣诞  白栎木
Christmas, white oak.
弗吉尼亚的
Virginia.
小时候约翰叔叔带我去过里士满
Uncle John took me to Richmond when I was a boy.
美国内战时南方联邦的首都
告诉我战争快爆发了
Told me the aggression was coming.
我跟你讲过我的树屋吗
I ever tell you about my tree house?
约翰叔叔建的
Uncle John built it.
谢尔曼开近的时候爬上艾伦树屋
Came up to Allen Station when Sherman got near.
美国内战将军  以焦土政策闻名
我吓得半死
I was scared half to death.
他说如果北方佬把大房子都烧了  我们就住在这里
He said we'd live in it, the Yankees burn the big house down.
你目睹过内战吧
You must have seen the war.
没有  先生
No, sir.
太小了  不记得
Too young to remember.
是啊
Yeah.
都不让人老实工作了  还能干什么呢
What's a man to do he can't work an honest day?
要卖掉这些鸭子  至少还得等两小时呢
Two hours at least before we get these duck off our hands.
给你个惊喜
I have a surprise.
沃德  别这样偷偷接近我
Ward, don't sneak up on me like that,
除非你想把孩子现在就给吓出来
unless you want this baby to come early.
给儿子
For the boy.
如果是女儿呢
What if it's a girl?
都一样  我只想给你看看
Anyway, I just wanted to show you.
来一个你打猎时的表情  沃德
Let me see your duck hunting face, Ward.
不
No.
让他看看你打猎时的表情
Let him see your duck hunting face.
治安官  我可一只也没有多打
Now, Sheriff, I didn't take one more than the law allows.
沃德  是你的夫人
Ward, it's Mrs. Allen.
你有儿子啦
You got yourself a little boy!
抱歉  沃德
I'm sorry, Ward.
我
I--
-她正在休息  -我就陪她坐坐
- She's resting. - I'll just sit with her.
现在不行  沃德
That won't do right now, Ward.
我儿子在哪里
Where-- Where's the boy?
沃德  你不能
Ward, you need to look past
一味排斥"精神收容所"
a crude understanding of the word "Asylum"
那里是很好的庇护所
and see that it's a refuge.
肯定有别的办法
There has to be another way.
她需要不间断的照料
She needs to be watched constantly,
必要时得强制喂食和洗澡
force-fed if need be, and bathed.
你能做到吗
Can you do that?
他连不让她在外面淋雨都做不到
He can't even keep her in out of the rain.
也许她会好起来的
Perhaps she'll come back to herself.
只需在这里签个字
It--It's just a signature.
我有笔
I have a pen.
带你看样东西
There's something I need to show you.
我出身于声名显赫的家族
My family was a grand family.
我找到了自己的生活方式
I figured out how to make my own way.
你自己也说过
You said it yourself.
太浮夸
It was a lot of bluster.
但这
But this is--
这是真实的
this is real.
这条河流  还有你
The river and you.
我早就该带你来这里
I should have brought you here before.
你好冷
You're cold.
你超出配额了
You're past the quota.
沃德
Ward!
说好是长期订单的
That was a standing order.
渔猎委员会来过了
Game and Fish were here.
他们告诉我如果我再从你这儿进货
They told us if we bought anything more from you,
就吊销我的营业证
they would take our license.
你觉得哈登法官希望
You think Judge Harden wants to find
星期天的早餐盘中空空是吧
yard scratch on his plate come Sunday?
有点骨气吧  马赛厄斯
Have some backbone, Mathias!
你疯了
You are a crazy man!
你想见识什么叫疯吗
You want to see crazy?
我让你见识见识
沃德
Ward...
我们走吧
Let's get out of here.
这里不再是我们的地方了
This ain't the place for us no more.
* If you see my mother *
* Oh, yes *
* Won't you tell her from me *
* I'm a-riding my horse *
起来
Get up!
* In the battlefield *
* I want to see my Jesus in the morning *
大火后那家人回来过没有
Has the family been here since the fire?
你熟悉周边水域吗
Do you know these waters around here?
这些钱够让你帮我了吧
This make it worth your while?
我需要一个河上向导
I need a river guide.
艾伦先生什么东西都不要了吗
There's nothing Mr. Allen wants?
不要了  沃尔顿先生
No, sir, Mr. Walton.
把房子卖掉
Just sell the house,
给露西女士提供最好的条件
give Mrs. Lucy the best.
沃尔顿先生
Mr. Walton?
也许还有件东西
Maybe there's one thing.
按你所说办了
It's just like you say.
露西女士会过上舒适的生活
Mrs. Lucy gonna be comfortable.
沃尔顿先生会安排好的
Mr. Walton gonna to see to it.
哈登法官让我告诉你
Judge Harden say to tell you
他们维护现存法律
they upholding the law.
市级法院不能与联邦作对
City can't go against Federal.
报纸上都登了
That's in the paper.
哈登法官把他的旧船借给你了
Judge Harden lend you his old boat.
让你留着
Said keep it...
只要你保证
long as you promise
时不时在星期天给他送只鸭子去
to bring him a Sunday bird every once in a while.
霍默先生说会把你的邮件寄到五金商店
Mr. Homer say to post your mail to the hardware store.
我会到霍默那里取你的邮件的
I'll pick up your mail at Homer's.
晚安  沃德先生
Evenin', Mr. Ward.
杰克  我得确认下
Jack, I just gotta confirm,
你要把圣诞赶出去
you got Christmas off the land.
罗伊  我一直在考虑这事
Listen, Roy, I've been thinking about this.
圣诞已经95岁了
Christmas is 95 years old.
很有可能会活到105岁
Probably gonna see 105.
他在圣诞节那天出生于[佛州]马尔伯里
He was born on Mulberry on Christmas day.
他是那个庄园最后的幸存者了
He is the last surviving member of that plantation.
他不是家人
He's not family.
不是血亲
Not blood,
但被释黑奴是有权利的
but freed slaves have rights.
约翰·艾略特·沃德亲自立下的契约
John Eliot Ward wrote that deed himself.
那不是关键  杰克
That ain't the point, Jack.
而且  圣诞都照顾不了自己
Besides, Christmas can't even take care of himself.
你要不给他送吃的  他可能都饿死了
He'd probably starve to death if you weren't feeding him.
还以为你会把这酒留到特别的时刻
Thought you were gonna save that for a special occasion?
没有比现在更特别的时刻了  罗伊
There's--there's nothing as special as the present, Roy.
我来问问你
Let me ask you something.
你有没有停下来仔细听过以前黑奴唱的歌
You ever stop and listen to the words of the old Negro songs?
他们唱的我一句都听不懂
Can't understand a word they say.
我唱首给你听
Let me sing one for you.
我要坐在那简陋的摇椅上
* I'm gonna sit in the humble chair *
我要慢慢地摇来摇去
* I'm gonna rock from side to side *
直到死去
* Until I die *
我要坐在那简陋的摇椅上
* I'm gonna sit in the humble chair *
直到死去
* Till I die *
你是个好人  杰克
You're a good man, Jack...
但记住我的话
but mark my word,
你说的正是
what you said is exactly what you're going to find one day.
你无法阻挡时间
You can't hold back time.
用露西送他的钢笔阻挡时代的洪流
Holding back the tide with that fountain pen Lucy gave him.
你的枪与雄辩已无用武之地  沃德
You've nothing left to prove with guns and bluster, Ward.
换种武器吧
Try a different weapon.
我写过几十篇关于狩猎的文章
I've written dozens of articles on shooting
还有超过两倍的抨击愚蠢狩猎法令的文章
and twice more than that lambasting the damn fool game laws.
我大概比任何人都懂如何引经据典
I probably know more quotes from English letters than any man,
不用扯牛津那套
save an Oxford don.
我可以说出
I can tell you
数十种羽毛的名字  颜色  用途与用法
the name, color, use, and disposition of a dozen type of feathers,
至少数十种水鸟的
and at least that many species of waterfowl.
我自己收集了很多南方联邦的钱
I have a collection of Confederate money I saved myself,
从战争结束前就开始攒了
beginning before the war ended...
还有积攒了一辈子的
and a lifetime of practical experience
在当今世上几乎毫无用处的实践经验
having virtually no value in the world today.
在我深爱的河流上度过了十五年光阴
15 years on the river I love,
而那该死的一切将我冲上了
and the damn thing has washed me up
我再也辨认不出的城市岸边
on the bank of a city I no longer recognize,
那里住满了我未曾邀请的人们
inhabited by people I don't remember inviting here.
赢了那么多次
All those arguments won,
结果现在看来我赢错了地方
and now it seems I've misplaced my winnings.
那就这样吧
So be it.
这里是我曾泛舟的地方
This is where I pulled my skiff.
圣诞  你懒到都不偶尔捅一捅火了吗
Christmas, you too lazy to poke at a fire once in a while?
我给你带了块巴布斯核桃派
I brought you a piece of Babs' pecan pie.
约翰尼硬要她做一个带去学校
Johnny made her make a pie for school.
我说除非分圣诞一片才行
I said only on condition Christmas gets a slice.
圣诞
Christmas,
我读了沃德在报纸上的最后一篇文章
I read Ward's last article in the paper.
圣诞
Christmas?
小杰克
Little Jack,
沃德·艾伦在理发椅上睡着了
Ward Allen fell to sleep in the barber chair,
不过在那之前  他立下了规矩
but not before he laid down the law.
他说  绝对不能
He say don't lay a finger
动他的胡子
upon his mustache.
"俄国大使对沃德·艾伦说
"And the Ambassador told Ward Allen,
你要是再敢回俄国
"you ever come back to Russia,
我会亲自把你押到沙皇面前
I will deliver you to the Tsar myself
镣铐加身"
in shackles."
"圣诞·穆特里比世上
"Christmas Moultrie knew Ward Allen
任何一个人都更了解沃德·艾伦
"better than any other person that lived,
虽然一个生来是庄园主
"and although one to the manor born
而另一个是奴隶出身
"and the other born to slavery,
他们却成了性情相投的挚友
"they were kindred spirits.
从小  我就和圣诞一起打猎
"As a child, I hunted with Christmas.
在河面上忙碌了一天后
"After a long day on the river,
圣诞会坐在壁炉前的摇椅上
"Christmas would sit in his rocker before the fireplace,
凝视着沃德的照片
"Gazing up at the picture of Ward,
慢慢地  细细地
and with delicate slowness..."
讲他的白人朋友"
"talk of his white friend."
圣诞讲了一个故事
Now, Christmas told a story,
每次都一模一样的故事
he told it exactly the same every time,
字字不差
not a word out of place.
但有一个故事他从来都没有讲给我听过
But there was one story he would never tell me.
我问了他几百次
I must have asked a hundred times,
沃德·艾伦是怎么死的
how did Ward Allen die?
我还以为他是想自己默默悼念
I figured he'd go to his grave without me knowin'.
但我没意识到
But I didn't see
我这一生中他都在告诉我这个故事
that he's been tellin' me my whole life.
现在
And now, well...
我想他一直撑着活下去
I think he was just holdin' on
是为了等我明白
till I figured it out.
那你明白了吗
Did you?
是的  儿子
Yes, son.
我想我明白了
I think I did.
我早就该带你来这里
I should have brought you here before.
看
Look here.
看我拿到了什么
Look what I got.
看这个
Look right here.
他像野牛比尔
He looks like Buffalo Bill.
是啊  很像
Yeah, he does.
沃德是萨凡纳河上最好的猎手
Yeah, Ward was the best shot on the Savannah River.
我有没有跟你说过
Did I tell you about the time
他有次射穿了露西画像上的双眼
he shot the eyes out of Lucy's portrait?
干净利落  就射穿了
Clean out, just popped them out.
看
Look.
看  在那里
Look, right back in there.
看见没
See it?
那是鹤吗
Is that a crane?
爸爸  你觉得沃德·艾伦是怎么死的
Dad, how do you think Ward Allen died?
儿子  一个人的死之所以重要
Son, the important thing about a man's death
是看如何反映了他的一生
is how it reflects his life--
只是他自己活过的日子
if it was on his own terms and...
还是有更深层的意义
if there was some meaning in it.
我觉得这其中是有深意的
There's some meaning in it, I think.
我觉得自己就在那里
I feel as if I'm up there,
追逐而去
pulling toward them.
追逐着某种
Pulling toward some...
遥远的目标
distant purpose.
* Oh, bring me a gator *
* Girl, when you come off the island *
* A ringtail 'ator *
* A Darien gator *
* Girl, when you come off the island *
* A ringtail 'ator *
* A Darien gator *
* Girl, when you come off the island *
* A ringtail 'ator *
* A Darien gator *
* Girl, when you come off the island *
* Ohh, when you come off the island *
* Wade in the water *
* Wade in the water, children *
* God's gonna trouble the water *
* If you don't believe I've been redeemed *
* Follow me down to Jordan's stream *
* God's gonna trouble the water *
* Who that yonder dressed in white? *
* Must be the children of the Israelites *
* God's gonna trouble the water *
* Wade in the water *
* Wade in the water, children *
* God's gonna trouble the water *
* If you don't believe I've been redeemed *
* Follow me down to Jordan's stream *
* God's gonna trouble the water *
* Who that yonder dressed in white? *
* Must be the children of the Israelites *
* God's gonna trouble the water *
* Wade in the water *
* Wade in the water, children *
* God's gonna trouble the water *
* Wade in the water *
* Everybody wade in the water, children *
* God's gonna trouble the water *
* Wade in the water *
* Everybody wade in the water, children *
* God's gonna trouble the water *
* Wade in the water *
* Everybody wade in the water, children *
* God's gonna trouble the water *